Inventory of the Carter Family Papers 1667-1862
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- People Files, 1667-1862. (Folder 1-102)
  - Carter, (Robert W.) 1792-1861; 1803-1862, n.d. (Folder 20-101)
    - Political Papers, 1773-1860, 79 items. (Folder 87-89)
      - Copy of a resolution for delegates representing Richmond County, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 89)
        Copy of a resolution requesting that the delegates representing Richmond County use their influence to have a law passed by the General Assembly separating the funds of Lunenburg and Farnham parishes, Richmond County, and appointing separate boards to manage each fund. Signed by Moore F. Brockenbrough and others.
      - Copy of a court order regarding the appointment of a sheriff for Richmond County to succeed William Settle, resigned, 1824., 1 item. (Folder 89)
      - Certificate confirming the nomination of Robert W. Carter to represent the counties of Richmond and Westmoreland in the Assembly of Virginia, 1857., 1 item. (Folder 89)
      - Statement concerning malicious reports intended to injure the character of Robert W. Carter, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 89)
        Signed by Daniel Garland and others.
      - Letter from William Wynn Stevens, at Washington, to Robert W. Carter, at Warsaw, expressing regret that his name was used in political propaganda against Carter, 27 Aug 1852., 1 item. (Folder 89)
      - Correspondence relating to the finance committee appointed by the Virginia Legislature to examine the Auditor's Office 1823; and the printed report and resolutions of the committee, n.d., 12 items. (Folder 89)
      - Draft of the report of the Joint Committee of the Senate and House of Delegates appointed to examine the Bank of Virginia and the Farmers Bank of Virginia, 1833., 1 item. (Folder 89)
      - Notes on the examination of the [Virginia] Public Printing by the committee appointed by the House of Delegates, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 89)
        Date of report not given.
      - Correspondence of Robert W. Carter regarding proposed changes in the mail route in the Warsaw district, 1839., 3 items. (Folder 89)
      - Copy of a resolution of the Senate of the State of Ohio regarding slavery, 1820., 1 item. (Folder 89)
      - An estimate of the population of the Northern Neck of Virginia, 1790-1820., 2 items. (Folder 89)
    - Notes and memoranda, 1826-1857, n.d., 31 items. (Folder 90)
      - Notes of Robert W. Carter on education, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 90)
      - Notes and correspondence of Robert W. Carter concerning government, including notes on the annexation of Louisiana and Texas, 1835-1857., 20 items. (Folder 90)
      - Notes of Robert W. Carter on internal improvements, 1823-1837., 2 items. (Folder 90)
      - Notes of Robert W. Carter on the right of suffrage, n.d., 3 items. (Folder 90)
      - Other notes of Robert W. Carter, n.d., 5 items. (Folder 90)
    - Diaries of Robert W. Carter, 1818-1859., 7 booklets. (Folder 91)
      The diaries for 1836, 1838, 1844, 1846, and 1859 are written in printed almanacs.
    - Administrator of John Mason, 1826-1839., 18 items. (Folder 92)
      Robert W. Carter, and Enoch Mason, were the joint administrators of John Mason. This subseries includes accounts, such as 17 bills for court fees and 1 letter concerning fees.
    - Guardian of Thomas Dent Mutter, 1818-1837., 86 items. (Folder 93)
      - Letters, 1819-1837., 56 items. (Folder 93)
        Including a letter from Thomas D. Mutter to Robert W. Carter, 13 Aug 1824, concerning the impending visit of the Marquis De La Fayette to Fredericksburg.
      - Accounts and vouchers, 1819-1837., 25 items. (Folder 93)
      - Other Papers, 1818-1826., 5 items. (Folder 93)
        - Carter (Robert W.), guardian of Thomas Dent Mutter, vs. Patrick Gibson, executor of John Mutter, et al, 1818-1822., 2 items. (Folder 93)
          Suit in the City of Richmond.
        - Haxall (Philip) vs. Robert W. Carter, guardian of Thomas D. Mutter, et al, 1823., 1 item. (Folder 93)
          Suit in the Superior Court of Chancery for the Richmond District.
        - Mutter (Thomas D.) - Reports of progress, 1825-1826., 2 items. (Folder 93)
          Reports of progress at Llangollen School, 1825, and at Hampden Sydney College, 1826.
    - Administrator of Williamson B. Tomlin, 1814-1851, n.d., items. (Folder 94-100)
      - Letters, 1829-1851., 243 item. (Folder 94-96)
        - Correspondence with John M. Chilton, at Vicksburg, Mississippi, 1843-1847., 9 items. (Folder 94)
          Letters concern slaves belonging to the Tomlin estate sold to Henry Lewis.
        - Correspondence and accounts of John A. Parker, agent for Robert W. Carter in settling the Tomlin estate, 1838-1848., 14 items. (Folder 94)
        - Correspondence concerning the debt owed to the Glebe Fund in Lancaster County by Williamson B. Tomlin, 1829-1849., 26 items. (Folder 94)
        - Letters, 1835-1851., 194 items. (Folder 95-96)
      - Accounts, 1814-1850., 196 items. (Folder 97-99)
        - Accounts, 1814-1850., 145 items. (Folder 97-98)
        - Williamson B. Tomlin with Robert Bailey, administrator of Jeremiah Garland, 1816-1838., 30 items. (Folder 99)
        - Letters and accounts of Samuel Woolland, overseer at Clifton, 1836-1839., 21 items. (Folder 99)
      - Legal Papers, 1833-1847, n.d., 10 items. (Folder 100)
        - Carter (Mary B.) vs. Robert W. Carter, administrator of Williamson B. Tomlin, 1843., 4 items. (Folder 100)
          Suit in Richmond County, Virginia.
        - Carter (Robert W.) vs. Henry Lewis, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 100)
          Suit in Madison Parish, Louisiana.
        - Overseers of the Poor, Richmond County, Virginia, vs. Robert W. Carter, administrator of Williamson B. Tomlin, 1845., 1 item. (Folder 100)
        - Parker (John A.) vs. Robert W. Carter, administrator of Williamson B. Tomlin, 1847., 1 item. (Folder 100)
        - Tomlin (Williamson B.) with Robert W. Carter, 1833., 1 item. (Folder 100)
          Agreement concerning the settlement of a debt.
        - Tomlin (Williamson B.) and wife, to William H. Tayloe, trustee for Robert W. Carter, 1833., 2 items. (Folder 100)
          Trust deed, covering a tract of land in Northumberland County, called "Clifton."
    - Chairman of the Select Committee of the Virginia House of Delegates on Banks, 1832-1837., 46 items. (Folder 101)
      Correspondence and memoranda.
    - Superintendent of Schools of Richmond County, Virginia, 1847-1849., 2 items. (Folder 101)
      - A letter from John F.B. Jeffries concerning his accounts, 1847., 1 item. (Folder 101)
      - Receipt signed by S.S. Hutt, 1849., 1 item. (Folder 101)
    - Treasurer of the School Commissioners of Richmond County, Virginia, 1835-1840., 4 items. (Folder 101)
      Accounts and receipts.
    Subseries 21: Tayloe (John) estate
  - Tayloe (John) estate, 1834-1857., 56 items. (Folder 102)
    Including the suit, Robert W. Carter vs. Benjamin O. Tayloe et al.
  Series 2: General Files
- General Files 1669-1861. (Folder 103-109)
    Subseries 1: Accounts, invoices, receipts
  - Accounts, invoices, receipts, 1787-1861., 20 items. (Folder 103)
    Subseries 2: Letters
  - Letters, 1713-1861., 51 items. (Folder 104)
    Items arranged chronologically by date.
    - Abram Farrow to Major John Holloway, at Williamsburg, 28 Aug 1713. (Folder 104)
      Note: The reply appears on back of sheet
    - William Robinson, at Richmond, to [?], 30 July 1714. (Folder 104)
    - [?], at Williamsburgh, to [William] Rind, [printer of the Virginia Gazette], 1 Nov 1769., 1 item. (Folder 104)
    - B.E. to Messrs. Purdie and Dixon, [printers of the Virginia Gazette, at Williamsburg], 1 Oct 1770. (Folder 104)
    - Charles Carter, at Ludlow Farm, [Stafford County], to [Landon Carter], at Sabine Hall, 24 May 1773. (Folder 104)
    - George Carter to John Cooper, at Rawleigh Tavern, Williamsburg, 1 May 1792., Copy. (Folder 104)
    - John Dorsey, at Baltimore, to [?], 7 Nov 1804. (Folder 104)
    - John Y. Chinn, at Lancaster Court House, to [?], 20 March 1805. (Folder 104)
    - Francis H. Peyton, at Leesburg, to George Carter, at Baltimore, 1805. (Folder 104)
    - Landon Carter, at Cleve, [King George County], to [?], 7 Feb 1806. (Folder 104)
    - Baldwin Dade, at Alexandria, to [?], 31 May 1808. (Folder 104)
    - Robert C. Maund, at Nomony, to his uncle, George Carter, at Oatlands, near Leesburg, Loudoun County, 28 Feb 1810. (Folder 104)
    - Bushrod Washington, at Leesburg, to George Carter, at Oatlands, [Loudoun County], 3 Aug 1811. (Folder 104)
    - Walter Jones to Robert Wormeley Carter, 25 Jan 1813. (Folder 104)
    - Samuel Moale, at Baltimore, to George Carter, near Leesburgh, Virginia. Postmarked, 16 Aug 1813. (Folder 104)
    - Fanny Lee, at Coton, [Loudoun County], to [?], 12 April 1815. (Folder 104)
    - G[illies] Thompson, at Saint Francisville, Parish of Feliciana, [Louisiana], to John Law, at Washington, 27 Jan 1817. (Folder 104)
    - Gillies Thompson, at Saint Francisville, Louisiana, to John Law, at Washington, D.C., 7 March 1817. (Folder 104)
    - John [?] DeHart, at Alexandria, D.C., to Mathias Ogden, at Elizabeth Town, New Jersey, 23 July 1817. (Folder 104)
    - W.K. Armistead, at Alexandria, to Capt. J.F. Heilaman, at Sacketts Harbour [New York], 26 July 1817. (Folder 104)
    - W.K. Armistead, at Alexandria, to Col. N. Pinckney, at Fort Niagara, [New York], 26 July 1817. (Folder 104)
    - J. Jones, Jr. & Co., at Quebec, to the American Gentlemen at Mr. Stuart's Hotel, [Quebec], 4 Sept 1817. (Folder 104)
    - G. Thompson, at Point Coupee, [Louisiana], to [?], 16 Jan 1818. (Folder 104)
    - Ogle Tayloe, at London, [England], to [?], 24 Jan 1818. (Folder 104)
    - Francis W. Ball, at Centreville, [Fairfax County], to [?], 28 March 1818. (Folder 104)
    - [?] to Benjamin O. Tayloe, at Paris, 1 June 1819., Copy. (Folder 104)
    - F.A. Carter to Mrs. Landon Carter, 25 Nov 1819. (Folder 104)
    - Charles Carter, at Corrottoman, [Lancaster County], to E.L. Carter, at Sabine Hall, 1 May 1822. (Folder 104)
    - William H.G. Dades at Dumfries, [Prince William County], to Walter Harrison, at Richmond, 19 Feb 1824. (Folder 104)
    - Charles Carter, at Clifton, [Northumberland County], to John Armistead Carter, at Andover, Mass., 28 Jan 1825. (Folder 104)
    - Charles Carter, at Corrotoman, [Lancaster County], to John A[rmistead] Carter, at Andover, Mass., 29 April 1825. (Folder 104)
    - Michael Ames, at Fredericksburg, to Robert W. Fentone, at Richmond Court [House], Virginia, 29 Nov 1830. (Folder 104)
    - B. Peyton, Adjutant General, at Richmond, to the Commandant of the 41st Infantry, Richmond County, 30 Sept 1831. (Folder 104)
    - Daniel Davis, at Fredericksburg, to Lewis Tiry, 29 Nov 1832. (Folder 104)
    - F.D. Peyton, at Social Hall, to [?], 22 Sept 1834. (Folder 104)
    - W.L. Marcy, at Albany, to John Campbell, 4 Feb 1835. (Folder 104)
    - James E. Heath to Augustine Neale, at Shandy Hall, near Richmond Court House, 27 Oct 1841. (Folder 104)
    - John Gibbs to [?], 24 Nov 1845. (Folder 104)
    - William N. Ward to William H. Tayloe, at Macon, Marengo County, Ala., 26 Jan 1847., Copy. (Folder 104)
    - Virginia [Tayloe], at Washington, to Elizabeth [Carter], 2 Sept 1847. (Folder 104)
    - William Hindeman, at Baltimore, to [?], 21 Feb 1850. (Folder 104)
    - John Critcher, Jr. to John S. Braxton, at Warsaw, Virginia. Postmarked, 21 Nov 1851. (Folder 104)
    - Coast Survey Office, at Washington, D.C., to Albert W. Carter, at Warsaw, Richmond County, Virginia, 6 Sept 1853. (Folder 104)
    - Benjamin Ogle Tayloe, at Washington, to George W. Lewis, at Claymont, Westmoreland County, Virginia, 28 Dec 1854. (Folder 104)
    - F.W. Pendleton, at Warsaw, Virginia, to [?]. 27 Sept 1861. (Folder 104)
    - E.L. Carter to [?], n.d., Mutilated. (Folder 104)
    - H.H. Lewis to B.O. Tayloe and W.H. Tayloe, n.d., Copy. (Folder 104)
    - F[rancis] H. Peyton to [?], n.d. (Folder 104)
    - John Popham to Major [?] Dulany, n.d. (Folder 104)
    - G. Thompson to John Law, at Washington, n.d. (Folder 104)
    - An unidentified letter, n.d. (Folder 104)
    Subseries 3: Other Papers
  - Other Papers, 1669-1854., 79 items. (Folder 105-106)
    Items are divided into two time periods, those belonging to the dates 1669-1789 and those of the dates 1823-1854. The papers are then arranged alphabetically by last name.
    - Papers of the period, 1669-1798., 30 items. (Folder 105)
      The papers are arranged alphabetically by last name.
      - Baley, (Samuel); 1718., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Samuel Baley to Marmaduke Beckwith. Deed to a tract of land in Richmond County.
      - Beale, (Elizabeth); 8 Dec 1766., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Certificate signed by John Smith and William Brockenbrough stating that Elizabeth Beale has given her assent to a deed executed by her husband, John Beale. The certificate is dated with the above date.
      - Brothwaite, (John); 1669., 1 item. Copy. (Folder 105)
        Copy of will of John Brothwaite, of Rappahannock County.
      - Dudley, (John); [1697?]., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        John Dudley and wife to Henry Curtis. Deed to 150 acres of land in Great Wicomico Parish, Northumberland County.
      - Dudley, (John); 9 June [1697 or 1698]., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        John Dudley and wife to Thomas Curtis. Deed to a tract of land in Northumberland County. Note: A deed of George Curtis, dated 9 June 1702, granting to William Lister his interest in this property, appears on back of sheet.
      - Dudley, (Robert); 1697., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Robert Dudley to Richard Farrell. Acknowledgment of debt. Note: A statement by Richard Farrell, assigning all his right in this bond to John Dudley, appears on back of sheet.
      - Fauntleroy, (Griffin); 1710., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Refusal of Griffin Fauntleroy to give possession of John Lloyd's estate in Richmond County to Daniel McCarty.
      - Graves, (Henry); 3 May 1763., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Henry Graves and wife to Richard Graves. Deed to 450 acres of land in Bruton Parish, York County.
      - Jones, (William); 1701., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        William Jones to Peter Coutanceau. Deed to 592 acres of land in Northumberland County.
      - Keeling, ( ); 1750., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Plat of land in James City County, bought of Keeling by John Dixon.
      - McCarty, (Dennis); n.d., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Certificate of the publishing of Maj. Dennis McCarty's intention to dock the entail of his lands in Richmond County.
      - McConnell, (William); 1772., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        William McConnell and wife to [?] Lack. Fragment of a deed to a lot in an unidentified town in Rowan County, North Carolina.
      - Minor, (Sarah); 1715., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Statement of Sarah Minor, appointing Thomas Batchelor her attorney for relinquishing her dower rights in a tract of land leased by her husband, John Minor, to John Champ.
      - Palmer, (John); 1678-1679., 2 items. (Folder 105)
        John Palmer to Edward Fielding. Deed to a tract of land in Northumberland County, 19 March 1678/9, and a copy of the deed.
      - Pavey, (Walter); 1680-1683., 2 items. (Folder 105)
        Surveyor's plats of land in Northumberland County sold by Walter Pavey to John Rice.
      - Pavey, (Walter); 1683-1714., 5 items. (Folder 105)
        Papers concerning descent of title to a tract of land in Richmond County from Walter Pavey to Daniel McCarty.
      - Pavey, (Webley); 1714., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Webley Pavey to Daniel McCarty. Trust deed covering a tract of land in Richmond County.
      - Sallard, (Charles); 1746., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Surveyor's plat of a tract of land in Richmond County, surveyed by William Garland for Charles Sallard.
      - Simpson, (Mary); 1702., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Mary Simpson to William [?]. Bond.
      - Stone, (Mary); 1774., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Copy of bill of James Davenport, clerk of court, against Daniel Morgan, executor, for proving and recording the will of Mary Stone.
      - Trice, (Thomas); 1798., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Thomas Trice vs. Francis Moreland et al. Suit in Orange County, North Carolina.
      - Virginia Council and Burgesses, 1751., 1 item. (Folder 105)
        Declaration of the Council and Burgesses of the Colony of Virginia to the King, requesting the reenactment of ten laws repealed by the King, and expressing gratitude for his approval of fifty-seven acts passed by the Burgesses.
      - Wright, (Mattram); 11 Sept 1695., 1 item. Copy. (Folder 105)
        Mattram Wright to Thomas Lloyd. Fifteen-year lease of a plantation in Richmond County.
      - [?], 1718., 1 item. Mutilated. (Folder 105)
        [?] to Richard Lee. Quitrent agreement concerning 904 acres of land in Great Wiccomocoe Parish, Northumberland County.
    - Papers of the period, 1669-1798., 49 items. (Folder 106)
      The papers are arranged alphabetically by subject matter or last name.
      - Berkley, (Carter B.); 1825., 2 items. (Folder 106)
        Certificates of lunacy of Carter B. Berkley, signed by the Visitors of the City Hospital, Baltimore, and by two physicians.
      - Chowning, (John); 1854., 3 items. (Folder 106)
        Resolutions by the board of directors of the Old Dominion Steam Boat Company on the occasion of the death of John Chowning.
      - Clark, (Randall or Randolph); 1823., 1 item. (Folder 106)
        Soldiers Claim of Randall or Randolph Clark.
      - Clay, (Henry); n.d., 1 item. (Folder 106)
        Subscription list for a dinner to be given at the Eagle Hotel in honor of Henry Clay and G.M. Bibb.
      - Commissioners in chancery, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 106)
        A paper by an unidentified person proposing that only one commissioner be appointed to each superior court of chancery.
      - Dickens, (Charles); n.d., 1 item. (Folder 106)
        A description of the author, Charles Dickens.
      - Fairfield races, 1836-1839., 1 item. (Folder 106)
        Memorandum giving dates of the Fairfield races.
      - Grave markers, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 106)
        Two sketches of unidentified grave markers, on one sheet.
      - Lyell, (Samuel); 1852., 1 item. (Folder 106)
        Certificate of appointment of Samuel Lyell as postmaster at Warsaw, Richmond County, Virginia.
      - Notes on agriculture, n.d., 9 items. (Folder 106)
      - Notes on the history of Europe in the sixteenth century, n.d., 1 memorandum book. (Folder 106)
      - Notes on the increase of population in Sweden, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 106)
      - Notes on the Mexican War, n.d., 1 memorandum book. (Folder 106)
      - Notes on a visit to Quebec, 1817., 1 memorandum book. (Folder 106)
      - Oysters, 1848-1860., 11 items. (Folder 106)
        Data on the oyster industry in Virginia.
      - Peck, (Walter John); n.d., 1 item. (Folder 106)
        Appeal to the judges of an unidentified court for protection.
      - Recipes and prescriptions, n.d., 7 items. (Folder 106)
      - Verse, n.d., 2 items. (Folder 106)
      - Washington Monument Fund, n.d., 3 items. (Folder 106)
    Subseries 4: Printed Material
  - Printed material, 1821-1857, n.d., 27 items. (Folder 107)
    - Statement of the Farmers Bank of Virginia, 10 Jan 1857., 1 item. (Folder 107)
    - Statements of the liabilities and resources of the town of Fredericksburg, 18 March 1854 and 30 June 1855., 3 items. (Folder 107)
    - Statement of the liabilities and resources of the city of Lynchburg, 19 Oct 1852., 1 item. (Folder 107)
    - Circular communication addressed to his constituents, by John Taliaferro, n.d., 1 item. Pamphlet. (Folder 107)
    - Speech of Mr. [Joseph Addison] Woodward, of South Carolina, on the tariff, 10 Dec. 1852, 1 item. Pamphlet. (Folder 107)
      Delivered in the House of Representatives.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1821-1840., 10 items. (Folder 107)
    - Other printed matter, n.d., 12 items. (Folder 107)
    Subseries 5: Unidentified pieces and fragments
  - Unidentified pieces and fragments (Folder 108)
    - Unidentified pieces and fragments, n.d., 13 items. (Folder 108)
    - Carter, (Landon); n.d., 4 items. (Folder 108)
      - Journal?, n.d., 2 items. (Folder 108)
      - On building a pier, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 108)
      - On taxation, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 108)
    Subseries 6: Label, covers, and envelopes
  - Labels, covers and envelopes, n.d., 64 items. (Folder 109)
    - Labels and cover from the original papers in this group, n.d., 55 items. (Folder 109)
    - Labels, covers and memoranda of a later date, including lists of autographs and letters, n.d., 9 items. (Folder 109)
  Series 3: Lot 2
- Lot 2 - Carter Papers, 1772-1793. (Othertype Lot 2)
  Presented by the Williamsburg Restoration through E.G.Swem.
  - Typed copies of letters and invoices of Robert Carter of Nomini, with genealogical data on the Carter family, from papers in the collection of the Williamsburg Restoration, 1772-1793., 169 pages. 11 x 8 1/2 inches. Typed copies. (Othertype Lot 2)
  - Catalog of 18 letter books of Robert Carter of Nomini in the collection of the Williamsburg Restoration, 1772-1793., 18 pages. 11 x 8 1/2 inches. (Othertype Lot 2)